Richard Harkness Templeton Papers
Richard Harkness Templeton Papers
1899-1952
Templeton, Richard Harkness, 1877-1952.
4.0 linear feet
Templeton was U.S. District Attorney for western New York, and served on the Buffalo Port Authority. Collection includes correspondence, 1917-1951; manuscripts of writings, 1899-1952; published materials, 1924-1947; photographs; and material on the University of Buffalo (where Templeton was a lecturer), 1907-1952. Other subjects include Allegany State Park, the Buffalo Port Authority, prohibition, and Republican politics in the Buffalo area. Correspondents include Henry Cabot Lodge Jr., S. Wallace Dempsey, James Wadsworth, and Mabel W. Willebrandt.
148702
Biographical History
Richard H. Templeton (1877-1952) was an American attorney. He graduated from Syracuse University with a Bachelor of Arts in 1899 and also studied law there. In 1901 he passed the bar and began practicing law in Buffalo, New York. He was a lecturer at University of Buffalo from 1910-1925. He was U.S. District Attorney for the Western District of New York from 1925-1935, and also served on the Buffalo Port Authority.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Richard Harkness Templeton Papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and published material. Biographical material is filed at the beginning of the collection.
Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing letters, as well as letters to and from others. Correspondence of others consists largely of letters written by Templeton's friends to others in support of Templeton's candidacy for District Attorney in 1924. A few other miscellaneous letters to and from others are filed following the District Attorney letters.
Subject file includes correspondence, bills and receipts, photographs, manuscripts, published material and related items. The materials filed by subject often are the subjects on which Mr. Templeton gave lectures or else they are projects in which he was interested.
University of Buffalo contains correspondence, manuscripts, and published material relating to Templeton's many years of association with the school.
Manuscripts contains addresses, lists, notes, and Mr. Templeton's college thesis and notebook.
Published material includes addresses, bulletins, cartoons, newspaper clippings about Templeton and others, programs, press releases, and a report.
Arrangement of the Collection
In Correspondence the incoming letters are arranged alphabetically by author and the outgoing letters are arranged in chronological order. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject or type. The University of Buffalo correspondence is arranged chronologically, while the manuscripts and published materials are filed alphabetically by type. Items in Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by type. The addresses are further arranged alphabetically by title, and if untitled, chronologically. Published materials are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Templeton, Richard Harkness, 1877-1952.; Dempsey, Stephen Wallace, 1862-1949.; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924.; Wadsworth, James Wolcott, 1877-1952.; Willebrandt, Mabel Walker, 1889-1963.; University of Buffalo.; Allegany State Park (N.Y.); Public prosecutors.; Buffalo (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Photoprints.; Photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Lawyers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Templeton family, 1966.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence
    - A-B (Box 1)
    - C-D (Box 1)
    - Dempsey, S. Wallace, Rep., 1924; 1928 (Box 1)
    - E-F (Box 1)
    - G-H (Box 1)
    - Ives, Irving N., Senator, 1951 (Box 1)
    - J-K (Box 1)
    - L-M (Box 1)
    - Lehman, Herbert, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1952 (Box 1)
    - N-P (Box 1)
    - R-S (Box 1)
    - Reed, Daniel S., Rep., 1928; 1945 (Box 1)
    - T-V (Box 1)
    - W, Y, and unidentified (Box 1)
    - Wadsworth, James W., Rep., 1945 (Box 1)
    - Willebrandt, Mabel W., 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence
    - 1921, 1923-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1928-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1942, 1944, 1948, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of others
    - District attorney appointment, 1924
      - A-C (Box 2)
      - D-F (Box 2)
      - H (Box 2)
      - J-L (Box 2)
      - M-P (Box 2)
      - S, U, W, Y, unidentified (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1928 (Box 2)
- Subject file
  - Allegany State Park
    - Correspondence
      - 1920 (Box 2)
      - 1921 (Box 2)
      - 1922-1925 (Box 2)
      - 1932-1934, 1940, 1951, undated (Box 2)
    - Bills and receipts (Box 2)
    - Manuscripts (Box 2)
    - Published material (Box 2)
  - Bill of Rights (Box 3)
  - Canals (Box 3)
  - The Constitution (Box 3)
  - Democracy (Box 3)
  - Law schools and their students (Box 3)
  - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 3)
  - Photograph (Box 3)
  - Photographs and negatives (Box 3)
  - Port Authority (Buffalo)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Manuscripts (Box 3)
    - Medal (Box 3)
    - Published material (Box 3)
  - Y.M.C.A. (Box 3)
- University of Buffalo
  - Correspondence
    - 1909, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
    - 1913-1914 Jan. (Box 4)
    - 1914 Feb.-Oct. (Box 4)
    - 1915-1916 (Box 4)
    - 1917-1919 May (Box 4)
    - 1919 June-Aug. (Box 4)
    - 1920, 1928-1929, 1933-1935, 1948-1949, 1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Manuscripts
    - Blueprints and plans (Box 4)
    - Drafts, addresses, etc. (Box 5)
    - Notes and lists (Box 5)
  - Published material
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 5)
    - Pamphlets, reports and bulletins (Box 5)
- Manuscripts
  - Addresses
    - B-N (Box 6)
    - P-W (Box 6)
    - Untitled, 1928-1929; 1931,; 1933-1935,; 1945-1946,; 1952 (Box 6)
    - Untitled and undated (Box 6)
    - Addresses of others (Box 6)
  - Lists (Box 6)
  - Notes (Box 6)
  - Thesis - Notes and copies, 1899 (Box 6)
- Published material
  - Address, 1945 (Box 7)
  - Bulletins (Box 7)
  - Cartoon (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings about Templeton (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings about others (Box 7)
  - Programs (Box 7)
  - Press release (Box 7)
  - Report (Box 7)